<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two twinnes: or Two parts of one portion of scripture. I. Is of catechising. II. Of the ministers maintenance. By Richard Barnard, preacher of the word of worship in Nottinghamshire</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850524</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15732</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1438:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two twinnes: or Two parts of one portion of scripture. I. Is of catechising. II. Of the ministers maintenance. By Richard Barnard, preacher of the word of worship in Nottinghamshire</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Snodham] for George Norton, and are to be sould at his hop neare Temple-barre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Galatians VI, 6 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Office --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Salaries, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15732:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15732:1"/>
            <p>TWO TWINNES: <hi>OR</hi> Two parts of one portion of SCRIPTVRE.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>Is of Catechiſing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>Of the</hi> Miniſters <hi>maintenance.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>BY RICHARD BARNARD, Preacher of the Word at Worſop in Nottinghamſhire.</p>
            <bibl>1 PETER 5. 2.</bibl>
            <q>Feede the Flocke of God, which dependeth vpon you.</q>
            <bibl>1 CORINTH. 9. 11.</bibl>
            <q>If wee ſowe vnto you ſpirituall things, is it a great matter if wee reape your carnall things?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>George Norton,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop neare Temple-barre. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15732:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15732:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS RIGHT Worthy, much-beloued, and ſingularly approued good friend, Maiſter <hi>Iames Riſley,</hi> all proſperous well-fare tending to eternall ſafe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR:</hi> I cannot but often thinke of your ſingular good reſpect towards me, in whom, as now it appeareth, long acquaintance in true loue hath bred a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant readineſſe to doe me good, not only when I am preſent with you (as if you were, as many be, a friend to the face, without ſound affection fixed in the heart) but alſo in my abſence, and that a far off, when I ſuppoſed (which was mine errour) my ſelfe leaſt in your thoughts, and therefore farre enough from expecting ſo great kindeneſſes as I haue now receiued at your hands.</p>
            <p>Surely, <hi>SYR,</hi> as I acknowledge that you haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently witneſſed on your part, beyond my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a minde fully bent to procure my well-fare, ſo I pray you out of this your true loue, to iudge me ready on my part to requite, if I were able to recompence ſo great kindeneſſes, vnto the full: but I am indebted beyond mine hability to pay; your ſatisfaction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from mee is onely my good will, and your owne friendly acceptance of a thankefull heart; a true
<pb facs="tcp:15732:3"/> token and ſure teſtimony whereof be this my late and laſt labour, which I bequeath vnto you, till there be more fit meanes of recompencing your farre better deſeruings. In the meane ſpace let it ſtand for a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my thankefulneſſe, which I haue euer deſired to ſhew vnto all, for euery little fauour receiued of any friendly well-willer.</p>
            <p>This my labour, in part concerneth the Laity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you may, in your place, occaſionally, be a very good inſtrument all meanes to further my intendment, for the maintenance of the Miniſterie. In part alſo it touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth many of vs of the Clergie, in our too much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected duty of Catechiſing; the Antiquity, vtility, and right forme whereof is here ſet downe; the godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of which I humbly recommend to my Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend brethren of the Miniſtery in theſe parts; to whoſe wiſe and indicious cenſure I ſubmit this my beſt endeuour in this point, crauing for it their friendly interpretation, and for my ſelfe their fauourable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, which I much deſire, and which, if I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, I will account, as an addition of Gods bleſsing to my Lords moſt honourable fauours; and as you, one well knowne and approued, ſhall be the inſtrument to effect it, ſo will I value it, as a part of high price in your vnfeigned loue towards me.</p>
            <p>Thus thankfully remembring my ſelfe, I commend my labour and my ſelfe to your friendly and kinde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, remayning</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much beholden Richard Barnard.</signed> 
               <dateline>From Worſop in Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinghamſhire. <date>Sept. 24.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15732:3"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PART. Of Catechiſing.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>GALAT. 6. 6.</bibl>
               <q>Let him that is taught in the word, make him that hath taught him partaker of all his goods.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He APOSTLE hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Coherence.</note> ſpoken of Charity, Loue, and tender affection of one towards another more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, here he calleth to their remembrance the care of the Miniſtery, which may ſeeme here by them, as now, to be too much neglected. The text is an <hi>Apoſtilicall Canon</hi> and diuine conſtitution, authorized vvith the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God himſelfe for reformation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The wordes are an <hi>Exhortation</hi> or a <hi>Charge</hi> giuen <note place="margin">The title and Scope of the Text.</note> by the Apoſtle in the name of the Almighty, the iuſt reuenger of all wrongs done to his ſeruants, who ſpeake in his name, vnto all that know and haue learned Chriſt, to maintaine his Miniſters. By this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15732:4"/> the <hi>Hearers</hi> are bound to care for their <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:</hi> by this the <hi>Paſtours</hi> haue knowledge of their right and libertie to take of the people for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and a warrant to claime the ſame, and to vrge the negligent to their duty herein, if they faile of it.</p>
            <p>This portion of Scripture containeth two things, as <note place="margin">The parts.</note> the parts to be conſidered: the firſt concerneth, the party to be maintained, enfolded within the Text, who is ſet out vnto vs in two things, 1. by teaching. 2. by the matter which he teacheth. The ſecond part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the party maintaining the Miniſter, which is plainely laid forth in the wordes: in vvhich wee may obſerue theſe two circumſtances: Firſt, the party ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted: Secondly, the duety which he is exhorted vnto.</p>
            <p>Now though this place ſpeaketh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> plainely of the <note place="margin">Preuention of an obiection.</note> Hearers duety <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ely, and but implicitely of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters duty, yet becauſe the peoples knowledge of the labour and painefulneſſe of the calling of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of that equitie, that labourers are worthy of their wages, may induce them to a more ready perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their duety; as alſo for that this <note n="*" place="margin">Preached at Southvvell in Nottingham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, by the appointment of the moſt Reuerend Father the Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Yorke, our worthy Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan and much beloued Dioceſan. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>verbum docenti vel in verbo Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizanti. Oecumenius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eza.</hi>
               </note> Text vvas giuen mee once, by one of principall authority in the Church, to vrge my brethren of the Miniſtery, publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſembled, to the <hi>duty of Catechiſing,</hi> I thought it not amiſſe, to ſpeake firſt of our ſelues, and our duty, that I might more freely preſſe our Hearers to their duty: if wee goe before, it is the more likely that they will follow after.</p>
            <p>That which toucheth the Miniſters in this Text, is in theſe wordes, <hi>Him that hath taught him in the word:</hi> The word tranſlated <hi>taught,</hi> ſignifieth him that is <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed</hi> properly, but yet is vſed and taken more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally for to teach or inſtruct otherwiſe, <hi>Luke 1. 4. Act. 18. 25. Rom. 2. 18. 1 Cor.</hi> 14. 19. and ſo muſt it be here taken, as Diuines hold, and therefore is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15732:4"/> tranſlated, as wee ſee both in Latine and Engliſh, by a more generall vvord of all tranſlatours. The holy Ghoſt vſeth the more ſpeciall word for the generall, partly to ſhew vnto vs of the Miniſterie, orderly teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the peoples edification, where we are to begin with them; partly, perhaps both to preuent a proud conceit in ſome Miniſters which may thinke that they onely are to be reſpected which doe Preach, as now Preaching goeth with men; as alſo the peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Catechiſing, and Catechizers, as if theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued not any liberall portion; but other perſons onely more excellently gifted, ſuch as can ſpeake, for tongue with a plaudite, for great reading with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for wit with ſingular delight, and for learning beyond the Hearers common apprehenſion, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of whom, <hi>Caeteri, non dico, poetae, ſed veri pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae ſordent;</hi> while Hearers doe meaſure all by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not by reformation of the heart: who harken after the tune of the tongue and labour of the lips, but not how men may be drawne to ſanctification in their liues: this is it which here the holy Ghoſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents, by ſetting them to Catechiſing, vvithout which indeed the people profit little.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> According to the generall vſe of the word, hence may be obſerued, that <hi>Catechiſing is not onely, and alone, the dutie of a Miniſter, but alſo other wayes of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and teaching.</hi> Hee is not onely to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
               </label> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 20. as Chriſt Ieſus and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, our perfect examples, haue done before vs. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> And the reaſons for it are manifeſt: becauſe the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is to reueale the whole counſell of God, to build <note place="margin">Acts 20.</note> them vp, as well as to lay a foundation; alſo as ſome need Milke, ſo others ſtrong meate: hee is one that muſt bring forth of his treaſurie, both new and old, varietie of matter fitting the Auditorie, for their increaſe of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15732:5"/> knowledge of Gods will, in all wiſedome and ſpirituall <note place="margin">Col. 1. Heb. 5. 1 Cor. 3. 2 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 3. 18.</note> vnderſtanding. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The people ſhould not bee euer ſuch bad ſchollers to need onely Milke, but ſometime ſtrong meate, ſo as they may encreaſe in grace and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord Ieſus. Therefore Miniſters muſt not only giue Milke to ſuch as be <hi>carnall, dull of hearing,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. Heb. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Babes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nexpert in the word of righteouſneſſe,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s habenteslacte, &amp; non ſolido cibo,</hi> which ſtand in need onely of Milke, but alſo to giue ſtrong, meat to them that are o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> age, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motiues. </seg>
               </label> which through long cuſtome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> haue their wits exerciſed to diſcerne both good and euill. Reaſon requireth this, that vvhen the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is layd, the houſe ſhould be built vp. Hee that is taught his letters muſt be learned to ſpell, and ſo to reade, and to vnderſtand what he readeth. Thus the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> went on with the people, as appeareth by his writings, and the places quoted. Much may be ſayd to this purpoſe, but my meaning is not to ſtand vpon the <hi>word</hi> here in the largeſt acception, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proper ſignification and ſpeciall vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the doctrine or poſition from which, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That it is a part of the Miniſters dutie to Catechiſe his people:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
               </label> This the Text ſheweth, where the Apoſtle ſetteth out the Miniſter by the name of a <hi>Catechiſer,</hi> and maintenance is here allowed for that worke of his Miniſterie from this place: other Scriptures confirme alſo the ſame, 1 <hi>Cor. 14. 19. Rom. 2. 18. Heb, 5. &amp;</hi> 6, 1. What need reaſons to perſwade to acknowledge this a <note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> dutie? Know wee not that euery wiſe Teacher hath his principles of his Art, which hee firſt deliuereth? Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are firſt to haue Milke before ſtrong meate. But to make this poynt fully manifeſt, let vs ſee what Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing is; for this proued, will afford ſufficient reaſons for this truth.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15732:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Catechiſing is a diuine ordinance, from olde time vſed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">What Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is.</note> 
               <hi>in Gods Church, as a neceſſary meanes, to informe the rud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſort, ſummarily, by queſtions and anſweres in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion.</hi> In this definition we may obſerue ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen things: 1. the <hi>authoritie</hi> of it, in this, that it is ſaid to be a <hi>diuine ordinance:</hi> 2. the <hi>antiquitie</hi> in theſe words, from <hi>olde time:</hi> 3. the <hi>neceſſitie</hi> of it, being a <hi>neceſſary meanes:</hi> 4. the <hi>vtilitie</hi> of it, ſeruing to enforme: 5. whom it concerneth, what <hi>partie,</hi> ruder ſort: 6. the <hi>forme of it,</hi> deliuered by queſtion and anſwere: 7. the <hi>matter of it,</hi> the principles of Religion.</p>
            <p>All theſe points being proued, are as many ſeuerall ſound reaſons brought forth to prooue poſition, or doctrine deliuered; which briefly may be brought into this one. Euery neceſſary meanes of olde time vſed and appoynted by God for inſtruction of his people in the wayes of ſaluation, is to be vſed of euery faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, as part of his dutie; but ſuch a thing is Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as ſhall in the particulars be proued: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be performed of euery faithfull Miniſter, as part of his dutie.</p>
            <p>1. I ſay it is a diuine conſtitution: for it is approued <note place="margin">Authoritie for Catechiſing from God.</note> by the word, as the former Scriptures ſhew, which is Gods immediate diuine voyce and authoritie: as alſo by his Church which is Gods mediate voyce and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, while it agreeth with the written word of God. The Scripture mentioneth both <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> here <hi>Gala.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>6. 6. 1 Cor.</hi> 14. 19. as alſo the <hi>Catechiſed, Luke 1. 4. Acts 18. 25. 2 Tim. 3. 15. Rom.</hi> 2. 18. It is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Milke,</hi> vvhich the Teacher is to giue from the dugge of Gods Word, as the Apoſtle did, 1 <hi>Cor. 3. Hebr.</hi> 6. 1. and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> vrgeth ſuch as were Babes <note place="margin">1 Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 2.</note> to deſire it. Wee ſee by experience that it is bleſſed of God to the diligent Teacher and Learner, that Sathan doth reſiſt it, mans corruption is againſt it, all which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15732:6"/> doe argue it to be of God, and not of man: what is of man, we eaſily make much of, but the naturall man ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth not the things of God.</p>
            <p>It hath alſo the Churches authoritie, euen all the <note place="margin">Authoritie from Gods Church.</note> Churches of God, from time to time, as ſhall be after ſhewed. Here I intend onely to vrge the authoritie of our Mother, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and conſidering Gods authoritie, and hers from God herein, I may ſay with <hi>Salomon, My Sonne, heare thy fathers inſtruction,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prouerb. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and forſake not thy Mothers teaching.</hi> Wee haue ſtatute law confirming, the Booke of Common-prayer impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <note place="margin">See Rubricke after Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> it: here God and the King doe ſpeake vnto vs. Wee haue Eccleſiaſticall Conſtitutions in the late Queenes dayes publiſhed, and now in the laſt C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nons, <note place="margin">Anno 1571. Can. 59.</note> by which Canon the negligent Miniſter 1. <hi>is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, 2. ſuſpended, 3. excammunicated;</hi> if he reforme not himſelfe. Heere God and his Church ſpeaketh. Wee haue this eſtabliſhed by the high Commiſſion in the Prouince of <hi>Canterbury, Anno</hi> 1576. as alſo by the ſame in the Prouince of <hi>Yorke,</hi> in Archbiſhop <hi>Edwen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> time, <hi>Anno</hi> 1583. Here wee haue the higheſt Eccleſiaſticall authoritie ſpeaking. Laſtly, wee haue bookes of Articles from our Ordinaries, in euery Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, for enquirie into this; and the Church wardens are vrged vpon their ſole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne Oathes to preſent the careleſſe neglect hereof. Thus wee ſee the authoritie diuine, both of God and his Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay, it hath beene a moſt auncient practiſe <note place="margin">Antiquitie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atechiſing.</note> in the Church from time to time, vnto this day. It was in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, and vſed in his houſe, <hi>Gene.</hi> 14. 14. compared with <hi>Cha.</hi> 18. 19. the Hebrew word tranſlated, <hi>brought vp,</hi> ſignifieth one entring into Rules or firſt principles: which <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ias Montanus</hi> tranſlateth <hi>expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuos initiato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> now <hi>initiatus</hi> is one that is a yong be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner in principles. <hi>Tremel.</hi> tranſlateth it by <hi>inſtitutos,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15732:6"/> and doth expound it thus, <hi>de religione informatos,</hi> and ſo vſed, <hi>Prouerbes</hi> 22. 6. It was in the Iewiſh Church, <hi>Rom. 2. 18. Catechiſed out of the Law,</hi> and hereto may be referred perhaps the place of <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28, 10.</p>
            <p>It is noted by ſome out of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> that in <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> were 400, houſes for Catechiſing, to which chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at certaine yeeres of their age were ſent. It was in the dayes of our Sauiour, who vſed it, Catechiſing his Diſciples, and other, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 15. 16. as alſo in teaching to pray, which is a part of Catechiſme. <hi>Mat. 6. Luke.</hi> 11. The Apoſtles vſed it, <hi>Hebr. 5. &amp; 6. 1. 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 1. 2. and Hiſtories make mention of Catechiſers, as an office in the Church, whereto ſome were deputed in the primitiue age; ſuch a one was <hi>Pantenus, Clemens</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>lib. 5. cap. 9. 10. &amp; 6. cap. 2. 4. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Conſtant. 8. <hi>act.</hi> 4. Bracar. 1. <hi>can.</hi> 35. Laodec. <hi>cap. 4. &amp;</hi> 46. Agath. <hi>cap. 9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alexandrinus, Origen:</hi> yea, Saint <hi>Marke</hi> Catechiſing in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> is commended by <hi>Philo Iudaeus.</hi> Auncient Councels ſhew this practiſe of the Church, in which often mention is made of ſuch as were <hi>Catechumenoi.</hi> Of this alſo ſpeake the Fathers, <hi>Clemens Alexand. Epiſt. 1. ad Iacobum Fra.</hi> Saint <hi>Cyril</hi> writ of Catechiſing. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> a booke <hi>de Catechizandis rudibus,</hi> but of theſe and many moe, read <hi>Zipperus</hi> his <hi>politia Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica.</hi> What ſhall I ſay more of the Churches of God? <note place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. 6. de Catechizatione puerorum. 3. part. decret. 4. diſt. de conſecrat. cap. 158. Sec. 8. lib. 1. de inſtitu. Clerico.</note> the very enemies of true religion commend this courſe of teaching: ſee Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi> his decree, and how alſo the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> hath taken order for Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sundayes and Holy-dayes. <hi>Rabanus</hi> doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend Catechiſing, yea, the Papiſts confeſſe, that the ground, which we haue gotten of them, is by Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, in the Popes Bull, before the Catechilme of the Counſell of <hi>Trent.</hi> Laſtly, that with their Churches power, they may alſo make ſome ſhadow, at leaſt, of princely authoritie, euen in this point, <hi>Caniſius</hi> Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme muſt come forth, vvith the authoritie of the Emperour <hi>Ferdenande,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15732:7"/> thus much for the antiquitie of Catechiſing, with the continuance of it, at leaſt in iudgement of all ſorts, though not in practiſe, through the Miniſters neglect, and peoples light regard thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſay, it is a neceſſary meanes; for that it is <note place="margin">Neceſsitie of Catechiſing.</note> the doctrine of the principles of Chriſtianitie, no Art can be learned without his Principles; we are firſt babes in Chriſt, therefore need Milke before ſtrong meat: can a houſe be well built without a foundation? without this the preaching of the word profits them little: what is it to exhort men to Faith, Loue, Repentance, and ſo forth, when they know not, indeed, what theſe words meane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boda</hi> mentioneth one returning out of <hi>England</hi> to <note place="margin">Hiſt. lib. 3. cap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Aidanus</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> complaining that the people profited little by his preaching; to whom <hi>Aidanus</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that it was perhaps, becauſe he did not, after the Apoſtle, giue Milke firſt: thereby ſhewing, that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth little good without Catechiſing: therefore is it neceſſary, that men may profit by preaching. Laſtly, the knowledge of the Principles is a notable meanes to preſerue in men the puritie of doctrine. Hereby they ſhall be grounded in the truth, be able to iudge of true and falſe doctrine, and not eaſily carryed about with euery winde of doctrine, as the prophane and ignorant multitude be, who eaſily turne as the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Cocke with the vvinde, for that they haue not learned any certaine grounds whereon to reſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſay it is very profitable: for it doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilitie of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing.</note> iudgement in the common principles of our faith; by which the truth may be tryed: Aduerſaries oppoſed, and ſtrongly conſuted. If the people vvere well Catechiſed, how eaſily might they ſee their owne fooliſh ſuperſtitions, and Popiſh Idolatries, which yet many ſauour, through the ignorance that is in them?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15732:7"/> The Apoſtle ſheweth, that by being <hi>Catechiſed,</hi> they <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 18.</note> learne to diſcerne things that differ: yea hence ariſeth theſe excellent fruits; grounded knowledge in the fundamentall points of religion begetteth right faith, and preſerues it from errour and hereſie, ſetleth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without inconſtancie, ſatisfieth conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſcrupuloſitie: breedeth zeale, and bringeth forth deuotion, and yet without ſchiſme or ſuperſtition, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning neither to the right hand nor to the left; for by their grounds they know how they ſtand, how they goe forward, whither they incline too much to a ſide, or doe ſet ſure footing in the right and auncient path of true peace. The exerciſe of Catechiſing will much profit our ſelues of the Miniſterie; it is as a hedge as one ſaith, <note place="margin">Rubbius.</note> to generall doctrines, and the touchſtone to try them: <hi>Catechiſme, Common places, interpretation of Scripture,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Foure generall heads of ſtudy in Diuinitie.</note> and <hi>Controuerſies,</hi> are the foure common and generall parts of the ſtudy of Diuinitie, but the firſt is Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme: without the laſt wee cannot well diſpute with an aduerſarie, without the third we paſſe as a ſhip vpon the ſea without a Rudder, or as a way faring man without a right guide; without the ſecond wee cannot learne well to diſtinguiſh, and without this firſt wee know not what wee hold certainely. Thus wee ſee briefely how profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table it is; both to Paſtours and people.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, I noted who they be that are to be catechiſed, <note place="margin">Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties to be Catechiſed.</note> to wit, the <hi>ruder ſort.</hi> There be two ſorts of perſons, which the Miniſter is to inſtruct: the firſt are called <hi>Babes,</hi> ſuch as be inexpert, dull of hearing, carnall and <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 1 Cor. 3.</note> not ſpirituall, which cannot beare ſtrong meate, theſe neede Milke and are to be catechiſed, whither they be yong or old perſons. The ſecond ſort are ſuch as be counted <hi>ſtrong men,</hi> being ſpirituall, hauing their wits <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> exerciſed, who can diſcerne of things that differ, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene good and euill, not onely in morallitie, but in <note place="margin">Heb. 5.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15732:8"/> Euangelicall truth; ſuch haue by long cuſtome an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of knowledge and ſincere iudgement, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare ſtrong meat. The firſt ſort St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <note place="margin">Epi. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Audientes; Tertullian</hi> tearmes them <hi>Nou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>olos,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine, Competentes:</hi> which are of two ſorts; one of yeeres, out of the Church, of which was <hi>Theophilus,</hi> the <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 4. Act. 8. and 16.</note> Eunuch, the Goaler, ſo one <hi>Heron</hi> a man, and <hi>Rha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> a woman, of whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> maketh mention; theſe were <note place="margin">Hiſt. Eccl. lib. 6. cap. 3. and 7.</note> catechiſed before they were admitted to baptiſme: and of catechiſing ſuch as were out of the Church, <hi>Aege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſippus</hi> ſaith, that by vertue thereof, there was neuer a Kingdome but receiued alteration in their heatheniſh religion within forty yeeres after Chriſt, ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent meanes is it to bring men to God. The other ſort of theſe are they which be now in the Church: which alſo be of two ſorts, <hi>Babes in yeeres,</hi> and <hi>Babes in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Babes of two ſorts. Heb. 5. and 6.</note> though auntient for yeeres: both which ſtand in great neede to be inſtructed in their Catechiſme. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is to be taught according to his capacitie, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer yeeres hee be of: ſo did the Apoſtle deale with them, as we may ſee in the Epiſtle to the HEBREVVES. It is loſt labour to teach prepoſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſly; it is abſurd and fooliſh to take one of good yeeres, to learne him to read by our reading to him, and not allow him to learne to know his Letters, becauſe hee is paſt a childe: ſo vaine is our labour in Preaching onely to the auncient in yeeres, and to omit to Catechiſe them, becauſe they be auncient; it was no hinderance we ſee to the Apoſtle: no more ſhould it be to vs. And thus much for the parties to be Catechiſed.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, The forme and manner of Catechiſing, is a <note place="margin">Forme or manner of Catechiſing.</note> briefe deliuery of the principles of religion by way of queſtion and anſwer: And in this doth Preaching and Catechiſing differ: Preaching is a dilating vpon ſome point, bringing it ſome time into a treatiſe: but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15732:8"/> Catechiſing is the contracting of the vvhole into a ſumme: Preaching is a large diſcourſing, vpon ſome Scripture with the interpretation, Doctrines, exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with application to all ſorts: but Catechiſing is a ſhort deliuerie of the grounds of religion onely to the more ignorant and ruder ſort. Preaching is not exacted to be repeated againe (though Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">4 Hom. ad Heb.</note> may ſeeme euen in this to haue tryed his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent hearers:) Catechiſing is exacted to be repeated, a deliuerie by Catechiſing, and a redeliuerie by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed; and that this ought to be ſo, the etymon of the word warrants it: For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is to teach, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by an Echo, the Teachers voyce reſounding againe, yet not onely the laſt ſillables; but the whole matter: ſo in Catechiſing there muſt be a voyce and a voyce, he that maketh the queſtion, and the partie anſwering.</p>
            <p>Thus did our Sauiour Catechiſe, asking queſtions of his Diſciples, <hi>Math. 16. 13. 15. Luk.</hi> 2. 46. ſo did <hi>Philip</hi> Catechiſe the Eunuch, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 37. yea, the people are charged to make an Echo againe. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 15. So did the Diſciples to our Sauiour Chriſt. <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. 27. 29. And that this is the right and auncient forme of Catechiſing, wee may iudge by all manner of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes publiſhed, ſet out by queſtions and anſweres, both with vs in our Church, and in all other Churches. Which kinde of inſtruction in this manner is much more profitable than to diſcourſe and dilate vpon a point Sermon-wiſe, which is waſt labour to the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as experience ſheweth, till the people be thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded with all; by vvhich the Miniſter ſhall diſcerne of either the knowledge or ignorance of his Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, yea, themſelues ſhall hereby be made to take knowledge of their blindneſſe, vvhen they ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue themſelues ſimple and childiſh in anſwering:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15732:9"/> this vvill ſet the people on worke to conſider what to anſwere, when, in the Miniſters teaching alone, they ſit as careleſſe and vnprofitable Hearers, as lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble experience doth ſhew. This will diſcouer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to themſelues, and preuent their ouer vveening conceits of their owne knowledge: and if they anſwere well, hereby they may be commended, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter comforted in adminiſtring to them holy things: yea, this will bring loue to the wiſe and diſcreet Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and procure him reuerence alſo among his people, as the tryall hath made the matter knowne to ſome. In a vvord, no way ſhall a Miniſter better know his Auditories beginning and growth in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; nor the people ſooner learne to iudge aright of their Chriſtian faith and religion, than by this fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and plaine manner of Catechiſing by queſtion and anſwere.</p>
            <p>Seauenthly and laſtly, the matter of the Catechiſme <note place="margin">The matter of Catechiſing.</note> is the principles of Religion, or a ſhort abridgement of the holy doctrines of our Chriſtianitie, called by the <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 12.</note> APOSTLE, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Elementa princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Sermonum Dei,</hi> the <hi>ABC</hi> of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or the rudements of the heauenly Oracles of GOD: or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>prima principia Sermonis Chriſti,</hi> the firſt principles of the doctrine of Chriſt, or the introduction into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſme, which be the poynts that we call the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme. <note place="margin">Foure maine points of the Catechiſme.</note> The heads whereto all particulars may bee drawne, are theſe foure, <hi>the doctrine of Faith,</hi> ſummed into twelue Articles; <hi>our duties to God and man,</hi> gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red briefly into two Tables, contayning the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. The matter of <hi>prayer,</hi> collected into ſixe petitions, ſet downe in that paterne of true prayer, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Lords Prayer:</hi> the <hi>doctrine of the Sacraments,</hi> the ſeales of Gods couenant, which are onely theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15732:9"/> two, Baptiſme and the Lords Supper. And thus we ſee into how few heads the principles of our Religion is ſummed into, which abridgements of prayer, &amp; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <note place="margin">Warrant for abridgements.</note> are made by God the Father, and Chriſt his Son, and the Creed by his Church, which manner of Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizing is warranted in the holy Scriptures very plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>VVee ſee how God brought the Law morall into <note place="margin">Matth. 22. 27. Eccleſ. 12. 13.</note> ten words, and Chriſt the ſame into two heads, <hi>Solomon</hi> draweth all his Eccles into a ſhort ſumme, ſo the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> brought the grounds of Chriſtianitie to a few points. The Scripture is full of ſhort Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes, <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 1.</note> which be ſummary collections of many things largely handled, ſee the ſumme of religion in <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 27. of the Goſpell in <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. the ſumme of mans dutie in <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12. 13. the ſumme of that which ſhall be done at the laſt day in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. The learned doe thinke, that this forme of teaching in ſo ſhort a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, is to be vnderſtood in the place of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothie,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſam forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, vel exemplar teneto ſauorum verborum:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 13.</note> as if hee had ſaid, I haue ſet thee a paterne of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words, for the manner of deliuering thereof, the heads whereof are theſe two, Faith and Charitie in Chriſt Ieſus. As alſo in that place to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 17. &amp; 12. 6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>formam doctrinae,</hi> ſo in an other place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Analogie or proportion of Faith, according to which we muſt teach, <hi>ſecundum menſuram noſtram,</hi> after our gift giuen, holding the rule of the word, the forme of doctrine, and the analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of Faith. Laſtly, this courſe of teaching, firſt the principles of religion, both Greeke and Latin Fathers haue followed, as <hi>Zanchie</hi> witneſſeth. And thus by <note place="margin">Lib de ſac. Scrip. in orat. praefix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. 34.</note> the full proofe of all the particulars, in the definition of Catechiſing, I haue giuen, I hope, ſufficient reaſons
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15732:10"/> of the poſition ſet downe, that it is our dutie to Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe.</p>
            <p>Hence therefore follow diuers vſes to be made of <note place="margin">Manifold vſes of the doctrine.</note> this doctrine to ſundry ſorts of perſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, vnto the reuerend Fathers, and all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <note place="margin">To Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</note> Officers, ſet ouer the Miniſters for to ouer-ſee them, not to ſee ouer Miniſters neglecting this ſo neceſſary a dutie. You are to ſee vs performe this: you take oaths <note place="margin">Motiues or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements to the dutie.</note> of Church-wardens to preſent this woefull neglect, if thereby the fault be found out; God forbid you ſhould let ſo great a neglect in Miniſters paſſe vvithout cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and controule: tythe not, I pray you, Mint and Cummin, and let paſſe this moſt weighty poynt of the Law of God and our King. Your neglect to puniſh vvill be our neglect of dutie; the Canon is very ſtrict, <note place="margin">Canon. 59.</note> it thundreth in ſound of words, but if you ſhall forbeare the execution (vvhich is the life of good Lawes) it may be <hi>terriculum, ſed vix ſane nostrum cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quam terricula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum,</hi> it will be as a Canon without powder or Bullet, ſtanding for terrour, but neuer ſhot off. The end of Synods is to good purpoſe in their right vſe, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of good things well eſtabliſhed, and for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of abuſes: Oh let not then the end of our mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting be that you ſhould call, and wee anſweare to our names, crying, here Syr, and there an end; as if the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Synodes were to know nothing elſe, but eyther whither wee had forgot or loſt our names, or out run our liuings. <hi>Sed quid ego edoceam peritos? pauca Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and therefore I proceed to the reſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to Church-wardens, that you preſent <note place="margin">To Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens.</note> ſuch as continue herein negligent: it is your Oath, great is the benefit which both you the elder, as alſo the yonger ſort, both children and ſeruants ſhall reape by <note place="margin">Motiues.</note> Catechiſing. Care for your ſoules, cauſe <hi>Archippus</hi> to fulfill his Miniſtery, reſt not with reading alone (tho it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15732:10"/> be alſo an ordinance of God) without interpretation, if you may haue it, nor with preaching alone, without Catechiſing, together are they ſtrong meanes by Gods bleſſing to bring you to God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to Miniſter, and firſt to ſuch as doe make <note place="margin">To Miniſters, and firſt to ſuch as doe Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, of which 3. ſorts. 1. The dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. Motiues.</note> conſcience of this doing it vvith diligence and profit to the people: goe on ſtill (my good brethren) you ſee it is a Diuine ordinance, your duetie, a neceſſary meanes, much approued, by law eſtabliſhed, by the Apoſtles practiſed, and by Chriſt himſelfe: goe on with the yong in yeeres, they need Milke, you haue law to compell them, and to enforce their parents to bring them (yet doe as much by gentle meanes as you may. <hi>Our Sauiour commanded children to bee brought vnto him, and rebuked thoſe, that would haue kept them from him:</hi> we are in Chriſts ſteed, command <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.</note> children to bee brought, and rebuke ſuch as hinder them: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> went from houſe to houſe to them <note place="margin">Acts 20.</note> in his time: familiar teaching profiteth much: winneth the peoples loue to the truth (as they get knowledge, for <hi>ignoti nulla cupido</hi>) it emboldeneth them much, and by your wiſe cariage, procureth to your ſelues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, thinke how they haue ſoules to ſaue and are the tender lambes of Chriſt, which you muſt feed, as you loue the Lord Ieſus. In going on with the babes in yeeres, draw forward yonglings in knowledge, the olde babes in yeeres, as much as lyeth in you ſuffer not them to periſh for lacke of knowledge: winne them by fauour, whom you cannot bring perforce: come to them priuately, vvhom you conueniently cannot deale with publikely. You (brethren) know, that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant mindes are a ſeed plot for the Papiſts to ſowe their hereſies, to ſet in their ſuperſtitions and to plant their abhominable Idolatries. Win them therefore to this,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15732:11"/> plant in them religious grounds, for ſo you ſhall beget in them a loue of the <hi>Word,</hi> a reuerent eſtimation of the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> and a care of ſanctifying of the <hi>Sabaoth;</hi> which three, they almoſt make no conſcience of, but through prophaneneſſe, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſet theſe things to ſale for a meſſe of pottage. Conſider how without the grounds of Catechiſme they cannot pray, they know not what it is, as appeareth by many, who account the repeating of the words of the Creed, and ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements to be a prayer. How can they examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and prepare themſelues to the Lords Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of the doctrine of the Sacraments? with what comfort can vvee admit ſuch perſons ſo ignorant (though liuing in the Church) to the Lords Supper, when the Teachers in the primitiue time would admit none but the vvell inſtructed vnto Baptiſme? Saint <note place="margin">Hebr. 5. &amp; 6.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> Catechiſed the Auncient, as wee haue heard: and wee haue a commandement in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer to admit none to the Sacrament vncate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed, which haue not learned their Catechiſme. I will not ſay therefore vnto thee (my brother) which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt conſcience of this excellent worke, <hi>Perge in virum,</hi> play the man, but <hi>perge precor, in bonum miniſtrum,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the part of a man of God, and a great reward ſhall be giuen vnto thee. And thus much to the firſt ſort which doe Catechiſe diligently.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of ſuch as doe this worke, are they <note place="margin">2. Sort negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. <hi>Ier.</hi> 48. 10. Reproofe, with the reaſons.</note> that doe it, but as guiltie of that curſe in <hi>Ieremy, Curſed is he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently;</hi> both in doing, and for the time they leaue it vndone: for in Catechiſing they do it without care of the peoples, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting, onely hearing them repeate words, but not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining how they vnderſtand vvhat they doe ſay, ſo as they are very little better for ſuch teaching, it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as good as nothing, as we may ſee where onely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15732:11"/> the people be thus taught. Againe this ſo curſorie a courſe is but a little before Eaſter, and all the yeere elſe are they le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to themſelues and neuer examined: this childiſh kinde of teaching bringeth contempt to ſo holy, ſo neceſſarie a worke, and the negligent paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it ouer ſo long, cauſeth youth and other to thinke that it is not ſo neceſſarie or profitable as indeed it is, in the hands of a cunning workeman.</p>
            <p>The third ſort of ſuch as catechiſe, are they which <note place="margin">3. Sort diligent, but not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable as they might be.</note> take paines, and that diligently, but yet, if I might ſo ſpeake with their good fauour, without offending, not very profitably. And this is either when one, two, or halfe a dozen, or as many as you pleaſe, are asked one and the ſame Queſtion, when by the firſt, the reſt doe learne to anſwere, though before they neuer tooke care to commit it to memory, and ſo it remayneth not with them, and the negligent onely care to giue ſome ſmall contentment for the time; or when but onely one or two, and euer the ſame, ſtand forth for all, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to two or three queſtions onely, for that time; vpon which the Miniſter diſcourſeth, as in preaching, which all the reſt ſit to heare in ſhew, but whither they doe or not, that is no more knowne to the Miniſter, then how they heare and learne his Sermons. I thinke (brethren) if I might freely ſpeake, it vvere farre <note place="margin">How to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the people by Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</note> better to heare euery one how farre they can ſay at the firſt time, then note where they leaue, and there begin with them the next time, and ſo on till they come to the end, all this time hearing them onely how well they can ſay: After begin againe with as many as can ſay the Catechiſme thorow, and examine the meaning, how they vnderſtand what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay, neuer diſcourſing, but inſteade thereof to turne all into queſtions, ſo ſhall you keepe the peoples mindes attentiue to you, delight ſuch as vnderſtand, with variety of queſtions, and make
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15732:12"/> them that are willing, to ſtudy how to anſwere the new queſtion propounded At the end to dilate, if you pleaſe, a little time, ſome halfe quarter of an houre, but not aboue, for the benefit of the more iudicious, it will not doe amiſſe. It is incredible to tell how this way both profiteth and greatly pleaſeth the people, ſo as both young and old willingly come thereunto, and very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly learne: I ſpeake by experience, bleſſed be God, for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi> And thus much to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which doe Catechiſe: now to them that catechiſe not.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> But before I proceede, it may be demaunded when wee are to giue ouer this catechiſing: or whither wee muſt be alwayes Catechiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>A.</hi> Surely ſo long as wee finde our people igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, as the holy Apoſtle did, for, though as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time, they ought indeed to be Teachers, yet being <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 5.</note> ignorant, wee muſt againe teach them the principles of the word. It is folly for a Schole-maiſter to put his Scholler into the Pſalter, that cannot learne his Criſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſſe-row, or into a Latin Author, when as yet he can hardly ſpell an Engliſh word, though hee hath beene neuer ſo long at the ſchoole. Moreouer, young ones come into the world and grow vp, who muſt be cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed: therefore muſt wee continue this courſe till our pariſhes ceaſe breeding a new increaſe, and the reſt be able to beare ſtrong meate: and this is not likely to be whilſt we liue, therefore the Church hath prouided for continuing of catechiſing without any ſtinting of time: but if any mans lot light in ſo happy a pariſh, hee may ceaſe this labour, and account himſelfe more happy than the reſt of his brethren. But now to ſuch as doe not catechiſe, and theſe be of two ſorts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſuch as doe not, becauſe they indeede cannot. <note place="margin">Such as doe not Catechiſe, and theſe are of two ſorts.</note> My aduiſe to them is, that as they ranne before they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15732:12"/> were ſent, ſo they would freely come forth before they be called, by Death, or the laſt iudgement, leaſt GOD <note place="margin">Such as would perhaps and cannot.</note> ſmite them dead, like <hi>Vzzah,</hi> for laying their hand vpon the Lords A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke without any warrant. Woe be vnto them, they be blinde guides leading the blinde, till they both fall into the ditch, that is, the dungeon of hell, where they ſhall periſh euerlaſtingly. Theſe be the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 56. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> and the <hi>Speculatores caeci,</hi> of whom <hi>Eſiah</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Neſciunt docere, non poſſunt latrare.</hi> But let them looke for their reward; hearken how the Lord calleth for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance <note place="margin">Eſai. 56 9.</note> by the ſame Prophet, <hi>Omnes beſtiae agreſtes, et ferae ſilueſtres venite ad deuorandum:</hi> All the beaſts of the field, and vvild ones in the Forreſt come and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure. Ceaſe therefore to doe euill, and learne to doe well, that the hand of the Lord come not out againſt you.</p>
            <p>Second ſort of ſuch as doe not Catechiſe, are they <note place="margin">Such as can Catechiſe and will not: To Preach and not Catechiſe.</note> that can and will not: and theſe be alſo of two ſorts, ſuch as vvill Preach, but not Catechiſe: and ſuch as will doe neither. For the firſt, which is alſo many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters fault yea, learned and worthily gifted, I yet wiſh them to conſider how aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kwardly they goe to worke, they ſet on a roofe, before they lay the foundation, or reare vp the maine poſtes and ſtayes of the houſe: they build caſtles in the ayre, they vvorke vvithout foundation, they ſeeme to feed, but famiſh indeed their ignorant Hearers; what mother or Nurſe will giue ſtrong meate to the ſucking childe? will they teach to read, without knowledge of the Letters? would God I might intreate them to proceed with their people, not according to their owne habilitie in teaching, but the capacitie of their Auditorie in learning. He that taketh children to teach, though hee be neuer ſo great a Clarke, yet will hee diſcend downe to them, weighing their weakeneſſe and not his owne vvorthyneſſe for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15732:13"/> better employment; for ſo ſhould he teach what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe knoweth, but not what poſſibly they may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: by which they loſe time, and he waſteth his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: and thus is it with many Congregations. The Lord perſwade theſe learned and vvorthy men to a more pofitable courſe for the people, and before God more comfortable to themſelues. Our Sauiour Chriſt <note place="margin">Ioh. 16. 12.</note> taught, but as his Diſciples were able to learne, not after his skill, but after their meaſure of concei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing: ſo <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> did the Apoſtle the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> vvho vvas a moſt learned Clarke, and able to ſpeake languages accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the places where he came. It is no diſgrace to Catechiſe plainely, learned Fathers haue done it: it argueth loue, and deſire in vs to haue the people to vnderſtand vs: A mother, ſpeaking vnto her lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle babes, ſpeaketh not, as to the elder in yeeres, but euen as a childe to children, vnto other, as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her to ſpeake, and fit for them to heare: To the learned ſpeake learnedly, to the ſimple and ignorant plainely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo ſhall both ſorts be well fed, and well ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Some there are vvhich will Preach, and not Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, <note place="margin">Vnprofitable Preachers.</note> but theſe preſume to Preach onely for a credit, and to preuent the name of dumbe Dogges, but, be it ſpoken with reuerence in this place, it is <hi>Aſinui ad Lyram,</hi> the prouerbe they haue not learned, <hi>Ne ſutor vltra crepidam:</hi> they goe beyond their reach, to the great diſgrace of Preaching: they doe read a Text, but flye from it after, as if it had in it the Peſtilence: ſome haue many good vvordes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no matter, as if Preaching were an idle prate, ſome neither good wordes, nor good matter. I ſpeake not this in contempt of any mans gifts, my ſelfe being the meaneſt of ten thouſand: but to aduiſe brotherly, that holy things be handled reuerently, that vve diuide the vvord aright (though neuer ſo plainely;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15732:13"/> ſo it bee to the purpoſe orderly) to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people, and grace of our Miniſtery: ſo ſpeaking with authoritie from the vvord, that we need not be aſhamed of the worke. Though the vvord be deliuered homely, yet if it be reuerently done, and the food wholeſome, it is to be vvell approued of all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirits, and of all ſuch as be religiouſly diſpoſed. But yet rather than the time ſhould be ſpent in vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable preaching, I could vviſh that omitted, till better preparation, and the labour beſtowed in this courſe of Catechiſing.</p>
            <p>The other ſort of them that doe not Catechiſe, are <note place="margin">Such as can Catechiſe and preach, but wil doe neither.</note> they that wil neither preach nor catechiſe, though they can or could haue done both well. Such are not reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vpon their Flocke, becauſe they be not <hi>cord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cum cura animarum,</hi> though <hi>corpore,</hi> with neglect of dutie: for reſidencie is thus defined by the Canoniſts, <hi>Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia eſt Clerici in Eccleſia beneficium tenentis, cum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate debiti praeſtandi ſeruitij praeſentia,</hi> So that it is not enough to be preſent in body among his Pariſhioners, but that he willingly performe ſuch ſeruice as the Lord requireth of him for their edification: and therefore ſaith one vpon that definition, <hi>parum eſſet, praeſentiam ſui exhibere, &amp; curam ſeu ſeruitium Eccleſiae negligere.</hi> This wilfull neglect ſheweth that they loue not the Lambs of Chriſt, that they be without conſcience of their dutie, without Chriſtian compaſſion, vvhich was in Chriſt towards the multitude: ſuch people hauing <note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> ſuch Paſtours, are as Sheepe without a Shepheard. If the loue of God dwell not in them that haue vvorldly riches, to relieue the bodies of the needy, and doe ſhut vp their compaſſion from them, how dwels it in theſe who ſhut vp Gods graces and gifts, and will not relieue the ſtaruing ſoules of Chriſts poore people? The world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wealthy may haue ſome excuſe, becauſe by giuing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15732:14"/> they diminiſh their goods: but theſe, the more they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, the more may they encreaſe in gifts and graces. How can theſe men comfort themſelues, vvhen they are charged by the Apoſtle, before God and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, at the appearing of the Lord Ieſus, to be inſtant <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 1. 2.</note> in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; and yet doe neglect wilfully <note place="margin">Iam 4 17.</note> ſo great meanes of the peoples ſaluation? Their ſinne is great, and great puniſhment ſhall be inflicted vpon ſuch as know to doe well and doe it not.</p>
            <p>Now (brethren) to you of the Laity; if it be our <note place="margin">Vſe to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> dutie to Catechiſe you, it is your part to come to bee Catechiſed, and to yeeld your ſelues to be taught: you I meane, that be yet ignorant of the principles of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <note place="margin">Motiues.</note> be not aſhamed to know the truth: Godly men are commended in Scripture for their humilitie herein, <note place="margin">Luke 1. Acts 8. Acts 28. Hebr. 5. 12. 1 Cor. 15. 34.</note> you haue an example in noble <hi>Theophilus,</hi> in that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Eunuch,</hi> in eloquent <hi>Apollo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted Iewes, whoſe grace let vs follow: it is no diſgrace to learne, as wee ſee by theſe, but a ſhame to vs to bee ignorant in the very grounds of our profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories make mention of the <note place="margin">Euſ. <hi>lib 6. cap. 3. &amp; 7.</hi>
               </note> Catechiſed, called <hi>Catechumeni:</hi> remember you aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that you are to be inſtructers and Catechiſers of <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 12. Exod. 12. 26. 27. Deu. 4 9. &amp; 7. 7. Pſal. 78. 3. 4. 5. 67. Prou. 22. 6.</note> your owne families, now how can you doe this, and be ignorant of that you ſhould teach? yea, <hi>Fathers</hi> muſt doe it, <hi>Deut. 6. 7. Epheſ.</hi> 6. 4. an example vvee haue in <hi>Abraham, Gene. 17. 12. 13. 14 and</hi> 18. 17. 18. 19. in <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo, <hi>Prouerb. 4. 3 4. 1 King. 2. 1. 3. 4. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> muſt be inſtructours, <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 18. example wee haue in <hi>Salomons</hi> Mother, <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u</hi> 31. in <hi>Lois</hi> and <hi>Eunice, 2 Tim.</hi> 1. 5. &amp; 3. 15. <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bands</hi> muſt teach their wiues, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 35. yea, euery one muſt admoniſh and edifie another, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 18. 17. 1 7 b. s. 11. Hebr. 3. 13. Rom.</hi> 13. 14. how much more then ſhould Gouernours of Families haue care of their owne houſeholds? If theſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15732:14"/> things moue you not, conſider how many of you haue ſolem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly promiſed, in being God-fathers &amp; God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to teach other mens children the Catechiſme, or ſee that they be taught it. If this dutie were perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, you ſhould greatly further the publike miniſtery, yea, by your ſound knowledge in the matters of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, Sermons would be better vnderſtood of you, <note place="margin">1 Iohn 4. 1. 1 Theſ. 5. 21. Acts 17. 11. 1 Cor. 11. 2 Cor. 13. 5. 1 Pet. 3. 15.</note> you would be able to try better the Spirits, to examine your ſelues, and ſo be made fit for the Lords Table, and not ruſh vnto it, as many doe to their condemnation. You ſhould be able eaſily to anſwere ſome aduerſary, to giue an account of your Faith readily, as you are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, if you be well Catechiſed; by the ignorance whereof, you cannot be but very vnſtable in your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, building without foundation: you loſe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of profitable hearing of Sermons, you eaſily yeeld to by-paths, and are turned about with euery wind of doctrine.</p>
            <p>But you that are of yeeres perhaps haue gathered <note place="margin">Anſwere made to ſuch as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt Catechiſing. Obiect.</note> excuſes, and thinke hereby to auoid this dutie of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Catechiſme: you are aſhamed to be knowen to be ignorant: Ah, my brethren, are you more aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the knowledge of your ignorance, then of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance it ſelfe? Know this, that your ignorance ſhall be knowne, if you ſo remayne in it, and God will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1. 7.</note> puniſh it, therefore now hide it not, but rather ſeeke to remoue it. Know alſo, that ignorance is a great ſinne, and wilfull ignorance a heauie puniſhment of God for ſinne.</p>
            <p>But that you may not be held backe by this ſhame, conſider, that all are firſt ignorant before they get knowledge; that it is no cauſe of ſhame to learne that vvhich we doe not know. In many earthly matters we can both acknowledge our ignorance, and yeeld our ſelues to learne, why not in heauenly alſo without
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15732:15"/> ſhame? the Apoſtles were ignorant, and deſired to be taught to pray, and many other things; ſo other in the <note place="margin">Acts 2. 37. &amp; 16.</note> primitiue Church, did confeſſe their ignorance to the Apoſtles, and the like did diuers after them to their Succeſſors, whoſe godly humilitie vve ſhould follow, for this kinde of ſhame ariſeth of a wretched pride, a ſinne hatefull to God. Doth not the Prieſts lips pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 7.</note> knowledge, and are not you to ſeeke it at his mouth?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But you will yet ſay, that your Anceſtors and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers had no ſuch teaching, and yet, ſay you, they did well.</p>
            <p>How well they did in that ignorant eſtate, in their blindneſſe, ſuperſtition, and idolatrie, I leaue to ſhew, and how they are, onely God beſt knoweth: yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they did, know you, you cannot doe vvell if you neglect inſtruction, for you haue the meanes which they had not; their ignorance was of neceſſity in thoſe times, but yours is wicked and wilfull, and ſo your condemnation the more iuſt, except you amend. But why doe you ſtand ſo much vpon your late Popiſh forefathers, and neglect your Anceſtors before them? ſhall the groſſe ignorance of the latter more harden vs in an ill courſe than the grace of the former in purer times ſtirre vs vp vnto goodneſſe? let this vanitie and vaine folly, and madneſſe indeed, be farre from vs. When theſe come into your minde, thinke whither it is better to follow them, than our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> the bleſſed Apoſtles, the holy Saints in their time, and our firſt forfathers receiuing religion, ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be Catechiſed when they were brought to the faith of Chriſt, before Popery tooke poſſeſſion of them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But peraduenture yet you haue this more to ſay, that you are olde, and paſt learning, and therefore will thinke to be excuſed.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15732:15"/>
            <p>Remember, that olde age acquiteth none from iudgement, for the man that is an hundred yeere olde, <note place="margin">Eſa. 65. 20.</note> and vvicked, is accurſed: vvee may not therefore liue wilfully in ſinne, becauſe we be olde. Olde folke, for preſeruation of bodily life will eate childrens foode, and are you too olde to deſire the Milke of the Word, for the ſoules ſafety? Againe, the older, ſo much the neerer the graue, and therefore haue the greater cauſe to learne to prepare for death, by knowing ſuch things as bee moſt neceſſary to ſaluation. Olde folke can learne ſuch things as be for the body, and can giue their mindes to remember them in caſes of need; why not then heauenly and ſpirituall knowledge? the cauſe is, for that indeed, they are like ſouleleſſe men, not caring at all what may befall them in the life to come.</p>
            <p>But to take this excuſe away, that olde age is paſt learning, there are and haue beene many perſons olde, which haue learned the Catechiſme: ſo as all old per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are not paſt learning, but ſuch, as indeed, are paſt grace, and ſo if they remaine, are paſt hope of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ancient in dayes, and the multitude of yeeres, ſhould teach wiſedome; and ſhall olde age now, not <note place="margin">Iob 32. 7.</note> onely be full of ignorance, but alſo a ſupporter of the ſame blindneſſe, in the middeſt of ſuch cleare light, and ſo great varietie of the meanes to bring them to this light? God forbid; to whom I leaue you, to bring you to a better minde.</p>
            <p>But if you be paſt learning, then from experience of your former loſt time, and inhabilitie now to learne, thinke vpon ſuch as be yong vnder you, ſend them, that they may not follow your ſteps, and plead ignorance and vncapableneſſe at your yeeres; ſaue yours, if yee cannot vſe the ſauing meanes for your ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But me thinkes, I heare ſome ſay, that euen the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their ſeruants is great detriment vnto them,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15732:16"/> for by being reſtrained of their libertie thus, they are not vvilling to ſerue them, and ſo hardly can eyther get or keepe them.</p>
            <p>(Brother:) If this be ſo; know, it is for want of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing: for if euery Maſter would diſcharge this due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as they by law and conſcience are bound; whither ſhould ſuch i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>religious ſeruants goe from the preſence of the Lord? But this is not euery where ſo, good and godly ſeruants vvill ſeeke to good and godly places, as for other ſeruants, if thou thy ſelfe truely feareſt God, thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as gladly be rid of them as they would be going from thee. <hi>Abraham</hi> wanted no ſeruants, though he had care to Catechiſe them, nor <hi>Cornelius,</hi> vvho was a deuout man, fearing God, with all his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde. Vſe well ſeruants, reward the well-doers, and thou ſhalt not want ſuch as will ſerue thee faithfully and conſtantly. As for libertie, afford it vnto them out of thy owne ſixe dayes of ſeauen, ſeaſonably and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently; and let them not robbe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord of his onely one day in ſeauen.</p>
            <p>Remember, that thy ſeruant ſhould be to thee more precious than a beaſt; yet what difference makeſt thou, if not in this matter of religion? thou feedeſt, yea, cloatheſt, giueſt libertie, reſt, warme harbour, and dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to thy beaſt, to haue the vſe of him for thy ſeruice, and if thou neglect thy ſeruants ſoule, doeſt thou any more eſteeme or make of him, than of thy beaſt, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king onely to his body, for bodily ſeruice? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou mayeſt not neglect this good of his ſoule; for who ſo doth, hath his ſeruant but as in place of a reaſonable beaſt, but not as a Chriſtian ſoule. See then Maſters what you doe herein, and you ſeruants, behold ſuch Maſters to you as Turkes, and your ſelues as their beaſt-like ſlaues bodily, and Sathans ſpiritually: but of this, thus much concerning Catechiſing, or teaching,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15732:16"/> the firſt thing to be obſerued in the perſon to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now followeth to ſhew what it is he muſt teach, and from what, in theſe words: <hi>In the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Word,</hi> here is ment the holy Scriptures, and more ſpecially the doctrine of the Goſpell, which in the new Teſtament by <hi>an excellency</hi> is called the <hi>Word, Actes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Acts. 14. 25.</hi>
               </note> 16. 6. which in verſe 10. is expounded to bee the Goſpell, ſo alſo vſed in other places.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Hence obſerue, <hi>That the doctrine of the Goſpell is a word of great excellencie:</hi> therefore wee ſee it here by a ſpeciall manner of ſpeaking to be called the <hi>Word,</hi> as if there were no word elſe beſides; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
               </label> and for further proofe hereof, the H. Ghoſt addeth elſewhere ſomething to ſet out the excellency thereof: it is called, the <hi>Word of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. 13. 19. Acts 13 26. &amp;</hi> 5. 20. <hi>Iohn 5. 25. 1 Pet. 4. 6. Heb 4. 12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Kingdome,</hi> the <hi>Word of Saluation,</hi> the <hi>Word of Life:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> For it ſhewes what Chriſts kingdome is, it is the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall meanes for our ſaluation, and cauſeth the dead to liue, according to God in the Spirit, vnto euerlaſting life; hence is it ſaid to be liuely, and mighty in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> This teacheth vs to eſteeme highly of the doctrine <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts 13. 48.</hi>
               </note> of the Goſpell, to receiue it with great gladneſſe, as the Church hath done, glorifying the Word of the Lord. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motiues. </seg>
               </label> For it is the glad tidings of peace, it is the onely curing Salue to the accuſing conſcience: the Law killeth, this maketh aliue; that terrifyeth, this comforteth; that ſaith, <hi>diſcedite maledicts, Away, depart ye curſed ones,</hi> but this <hi>venite benedicts, Oh come ye bleſſed of the Lord, receiue the kingdome prepared for you;</hi> that is the law of bondage; this of libertie: therein we behold onely the Iuſtice of God, and our miſerie, herein our happie deliuerance, and Gods great vnſpeakeable mercy. Bleſſe the Lord therefore, and let them be made much of, who bring theſe glad tydings of great ioy vnto all his people, for beautifull are their feet. <note place="margin">Eſa. 52. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:15732:17"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Secondly, hence may vvee obſerue, <hi>That the Word of God is the matter of the Miniſtery, for the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the people:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
               </label> vvhich may appeare moſt true by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Matthew 28. 20. 2 Timoth. 4. 2. 1 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinth,</hi> 4. 6. and the example of Chriſt, in teaching, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 28. and alſo his Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 22. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> For it onely maketh knowne his Will vnto vs, and is the inſtrument of conuerſion, by which the ſpirit vvork<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">Luke 11. 28. Reuel. 1. 3.</note> effectually in all ſuch as are ordayned to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and maketh bleſſed ſuch as beleeue and obey the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Let vs then of the Miniſtery, ſtudy the Scriptures, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 13. Motiues. 2 <hi>Pet. 1. Acts 26. 18.</hi>
               </note> and giue attendance to the reading of them, to exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and doctrine out of them: for it onely is a <hi>ſure Word,</hi> it conuerteth the Soule, turning man from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to light, from Sathan vnto God, and a word <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> mighty in operation to <hi>diſcouer man vnto himſelfe,</hi> to make him throw downe himſelfe, and caſt down euery <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.</note> imagination and high thought exalted againſt GOD, and to bring them into obedience. It maketh vs wiſe, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> and perfect to euery good worke, and it is ſufficient for inſtruction, correction, confutation and doctrine; and this onely is it, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reprehenſion. </seg>
               </label> which God hath appointed, and which he will aſſiſt with his ſpirit, in ſauing his people.</p>
            <p>This iuſtly condemneth thoſe of a fault, who being Miniſters, yet ſtudy leaſt the Scriptures, as if they were too ſhallow for their deepe wits, and too vulgarly knowne for them to beſtow their ſtudies in, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore delight neither in reading, nor teaching vvhat they ſay, but vvhat man ſayth, but as theſe ſeeke themſelues, ſo they looſe the Lord, and authoritie in the hearts of his people; <hi>videant ipſi,</hi> they haue their reward.</p>
            <p>The poſition or doctrine being true, it alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the practiſe of our aduerſaries, vvho feede
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15732:17"/> their auditories with vaine Philoſophie, lying Legends, Poeticall fictions, dreames, and Sophiſticall &amp; Schoole quidities, Popiſh decrees, and humane Conſtitutions, which is to infect and poyſon the people vvith falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, errours, ſuperſtition and Idoll ſeruice, fit for that Antichriſt, &amp; not to feed the flocke of Chriſt with wholeſome doctrine, which theſe little regard, and ſo all ſuch as delight onely to tickle the eare, to get to themſelues a prayſe of humane eloquence, or to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>ſayings</hi> here and there, and euery where, except the ſayings of Chriſt, his Prophets and Apoſtles, Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha before, and more often then the Canon of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Which I ſpeake not any way to derogate from the iuſt prayſes of learning and eloquence: they are Gods excellent gifts to be honoured and commended; for the Miniſtery neceſſary, and in the Preaching of the word to be vſed, ſo it be in ſpirituall vviſedome, and in that holy grace of humilitie, for the Churches edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and not our owne prayſe, ſo in <hi>ſome caſes,</hi> before <hi>ſome kinde of auditory,</hi> in handling of <hi>ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> to vſe Philoſophie, teſtimonies humane is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, as the learned ſhew, and elſe-where my ſelfe <note place="margin">In the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Shepheard.</note> haue publiſhed, which I note, leſt here I be miſtaken. And thus much for the firſt part of my Text concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs of the Miniſtery.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15732:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE SECOND PART. Of the</hi> Miniſters <hi>maintenance.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow followeth the ſecond part, which <note place="margin">Second part of the Text.</note> concerneth the people, vvho are to maintaine the Miniſtery, wherein were obſerued two circumſtances: firſt, the partie exhorted: ſecondly, the duety to be performed.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, the perſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to maintaine the MINISTER, is euery one, without any exception, that is taught in the word: the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is properly ment of ſuch a one as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by word of mouth in the Chriſtian faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be Baptiſed, which was the Churches cuſtome, when perſons of yeeres were conuerted to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion: but here it is taken for all hearers, ſuch as be in their Catechiſme, and ſuch as be more expert in the word, whither they be inſtructed publikely or priuately of their Paſtours and Miniſters: ſo the word is vſed, as well for thoſe in the Church, as for thoſe that are to be admitted into the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 18. Where the Apoſtle calleth a Teacher of the law, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And therefore here it is, as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, you <hi>Galatians,</hi> vvhich haue Teachers inſtructing you, giuing either to the weaker Milke, or to other ſtrong meate, you, ſo taught, are to maintaine them for that their office and Miniſtery.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15732:18"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Whence we may obſerue, <hi>That the learner is to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his Teacher, the Catechiſed the Catechiſer, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioner his Paſtour, the Hearer of what degree ſoeuer his Inſtructour.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
               </label> This is the principall point here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in theſe vvordes, which is further proued by this ſame Apoſtle, by many reaſons elſe-where, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> This is an Apoſtolicall conſtitution, and the Lords ordinance, for the maintenance of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnder the Goſpell, as well as vnder the law, that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters may be encouraged in the execution of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and that there may be a continuance of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, which without maintenance would not be.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Therefore you our Hearers are to make conſcience of this duetie, which make no conſcience of it, and you that doe make conſcience thereof, to continue ſo ſtill. <note place="margin">Foure princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall dueties people owe to their Teachers.</note> There be foure principall dueties vvhich you the people are to performe to their Paſtours, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; <hi>the firſt is to heare them,</hi> which all but Atheiſts and Papiſts vvill doe, vaine Sectaries, idle-headed Schiſmatickes, and ſuch alſo among vs, which be in loue vvith their ſinnes, and ſo cannot away to heare them ſpoken againſt. The <hi>ſecond is to reuerence their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> receiuing them as Chriſts Ambaſſadours; which the truely conuerted will doe, but the proud and prophane will not. The third is <hi>to obey them,</hi> and ſubmit your ſelues vnto them, <hi>in the Lord;</hi> which onely thoſe refuſe, who cannot away to be reſtrayned from their liberty of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The fourth is <hi>to loue and to allow them maintenance,</hi> which the couetous worldling cannot away to heare of.</p>
            <p>But to moue you, let theſe reaſons preuaile with you. Paſtours are ſpirituall parents, who beget men vnto <note place="margin">Motiues. 1 <hi>Cor. 4. 15. Phil. Verſ.</hi> 19. People muſt maintaine their Paſtours. <hi>Deut. 25. 4.</hi>
               </note> God, who therefore doe owe themſelues vnto them, as children vnto Parents. It is the Law of Nations, and a common equitie, that ſuch as labour for the common good of all, ſhould be maintained by them all: this man
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15732:19"/> yeeldeth to the labouring Oxe, and the law ſo prouided. It is a charge laid vpon you by Gods Law, <hi>Deut 12. 19. 1 Tim.</hi> 5. 17. and this is grounded vpon the former common equitie, <hi>verſe</hi> 18. Euery trade and calling is able to maintaine them, that honeſtly with diligence labour therein. And is the Miniſterie ſo baſe, as that it ſhould ſet the Miniſters on begging, which attend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it? He that goeth on vvarrefare liueth not on his owne coſt, the labourer hath his hyre, the Shepheard feedes of the Milke of the flocke: Now, Miniſters are watchmen, labourers in the Lords Vineyard, and Shepherds ſet ouer their flockes, and therefore are to eate of the fruit of the Vines, and to receiue mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from their flockes, ouer which the Lord hath ſet them.</p>
            <p>Miniſters are to giue themſelues ſtudiouſly to their <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 4.</note> miniſtrie, and not to be intangled with the cares of this world: therefore muſt others care for them, to preuent <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 14.</note> their cares. The Lord hath ſet this downe, that hee which preacheth the Goſpell ſhould <hi>liue of the Goſpell.</hi> Is a meſſenger of ſaluation, of glad tidings of peace, leſſe to be regarded then the Miniſters of the Law and death, who were well and very liberally prouided for among the people of God vnder the Law? See then (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) that Nature, common equity, and the word of God doth binde you to prouide for, and to maintaine your Miniſters, by whom you are taught in the word: and thus much for the perſon which is to maintaine the Miniſter, euen euery one, higher or lower, richer or in ſome meaner eſtate, are to ioyne together herein.</p>
            <p>The ſecond circumſtance is that vvhereunto this party is exhorted, and that is to make his Teacher <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ker of or in all his goods.</hi> Whence we may obſerue this Doctrine: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That maintenance is allowed by the Lord or the Miniſtery of the Goſpell, and Preaching of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15732:19"/> word:</hi> this is proued in, 1 <hi>Cor 9. 14. 1 Tim.</hi> 5. 17. <note place="margin">Proofe. <hi>Epheſ. 4. 2 Cor.</hi> 5. Reaſon. Vſe.</note> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 10. 10. Becauſe it is a calling ordained of God, and Miniſters are his meſſengers and ſeruants, and the labour of the Miniſtery is vvorthy of vvages, and a worke deſeruing a great reward. Acknowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this truth. For if you will confeſſe maintenance due, you will then bethinke your ſelues peraduenture how you may giue them maintenance. For hee that granteth maintenance, muſt alſo afford maintenance, as his iudgement is informed for the one, ſo his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhould pricke him forward to the other, but I take this as agreed vpon on all hands, (except any be poſſeſſed vvith an Anabaptiſticall ſpirit, denying any need of the office of a publicke Teacher) that it is fit that the Miniſter of CHRIST be maintained; but the doubt is of the <hi>manner,</hi> and of the <hi>meanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this doubt may be remoued, and your mindes ſetled, if indeed you dally not with GOD and your owne conſciences herein, three things will I proue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Three points handled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the maintenance of Miniſters. Doct. Proofe. 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 5. 17. Miniſters ought liberally to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</note> you: firſt, that this maintenance muſt be <hi>liberall:</hi> ſecondly <hi>certaine,</hi> and thirdly, that the beſt meanes is, to be maintained <hi>by Tythes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The painefull Preachers of the Goſpell are liberally to be maintained,</hi> this is a part of their double honour; in beggarly maintenance is no honour, but baſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; here in this Text the Apoſtle vvilleth their Hearers to make them <hi>partakers of all their goods,</hi> this is a large allowance. The Miniſtery of the Goſpell is more excellent than the Miniſtery of the Law, and therefore if the Lord iudged them vvorthy of a very great allowance for their labour in their ſeruice for the Tabernacle, how much greater now are the Miniſters of the Goſpell worthy of? But ſee how li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall <note place="margin">The Lords liberall allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Leuites.</note> the Lord vvas to the Prieſts and Leuites. The whole Land of promiſe, was but as a fourth part to all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15732:20"/> England in compaſſe, yet did the Lord allow for their maintenance, and their families.</p>
            <p>Firſt, forty eight Cities with the Suburbs, to dwell <note place="margin">Num. 35. 4. 5. 7.</note> in, that their families after their death might not bee expoſed to the cruell world and mercileſſe mindes of men, to ſeeke harbour and homeſteedes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they had tythes of all things, of Corne, <note place="margin">Leu. 27. 30. 32.</note> Fruit, Catle, Sheepe, &amp;c: euen tythes of all, as <hi>Iacob</hi> vowed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. 22.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the firſt borne of Man and Beaſt was theirs, <note place="margin">Exod. 34. 19. 20.</note> as appeareth by many places.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, all the firſt fruits vvere due vnto them. <note place="margin">Ezec. 44. 30. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he. 10. 36. Num. 18. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Num. 18. 13. Deut. 18. 4. Ezec. 44. 30. Neh.</hi> 10. 35. 37.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, all oblations and vowes whatſoeuer was dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God, and ſeparated from a common vſe. <hi>Num. 18. 8. 14. 19. Ezec.</hi> 44. 29. 30.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, ſinne Offerings, heaue Offerings, ſhake Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and the Shew-bread. <hi>Num. 18. 9. 11. Ezec. 44. 29. Leuit.</hi> 24. 9.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, of the ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing, they had the breſt and the ſhoulder, of other, the ſhoulder the two cheekes and maw: and of burnt offerings the skin. <hi>Numb. 18. 18. Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 7. 31. 32. 34.</p>
            <p>Eightly, they reaped benefit by the yeerely appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Males, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 15. and 34. 20. and by other occaſions, <hi>Leu.</hi> 5. 15. 16.</p>
            <p>If therefore wee account double honour, partaking of all your goods, and this the Lords bountie to the Leuites liberall maintenance, then are wee now libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to be maintayned. For the Miniſterie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, is as worthy of it, as the Miniſterie of the law, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are to be liberall, and plentifull in good workes, how can they doe this, if they be not liberally main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained? It is alſo not a little meanes to procure to them that reuerence which is due to them, and ſo to preuent contempt.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15732:20"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Therefore you ſee that you are not onely to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motiues. </seg>
               </label> but liberally alſo. So ſhall you encourage them in their Miniſtery; ſtir vp other, in hope, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Miniſters; make them able to ſhew forth good workes of mercy vnto the poore; and ſo get them fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and countenance before the people. In the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church profeſſours were exceeding large han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Church; and our latter Aunceſtours ſpared not any coſt to doe good to the Church. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reprehenſion. </seg>
               </label> Which iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproueth and condemneth now in our age, the ſparing and niggardly hand of moſt tovvards the Church; in other (too many) their Robbing and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledgious hands layd vpon the goods of the Church; who profeſſe religion in policie, and not in Pietie; and can allow <hi>Michaes</hi> wages, perhaps ten ſhekels of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, <note place="margin">Iudg. 17.</note> a ſuite of apparrell, and meate, and drincke, and bleſſe themſelues for their bounty, if any of theſe come to twenty nobles, ten, or twenty pounds, as peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they will in ſome caſes (<hi>viz.</hi> that by ſuch a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance they may poſſeſſe many hundreds of pounds, as ſome doe,) Oh how bountifull <hi>Latrones,</hi> I ſhould ſay <hi>Patrons,</hi> be they? for vvhy? they and the like doe iudge out of their charitable pietie, twentie pounds a ſufficient allowance. And it may be ſo; to ſuch baſe fellowes perhaps as they preſent, who are almoſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnlearned, vnfit for the Miniſtery, and who neuer knew how otherwiſe they could get ten pounds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great bodily paines; no maruaile, that ſuch can be willing to take twenty pounds yeerely for a Parſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age worth fifteene ſcore: horrible Symonie, ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>crable <note place="margin">The Parſon and a Cheuerill conſcience hath met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt worthy a Plum-tree.</note> Sacriledge! The Canker-worme of Gods heauie curſe ſeaze vpon ſuch poſſeſſed prayes, and eate vp their ſubſtance, til they ceaſe to doe ſo wickedly. But (Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robber) tell mee, if the Incumbent be learned, and a painefull godly Teacher, is this thy allowance ſufficient?
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15732:21"/> I demand why then thou art ſo greedy, ſo immeaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably gaping for more? parhaps thou haſt two hundred, fiue hundred, or a thouſand pounds by yeere of thine owne lands and leaſes, a full temporall eſtate (if there were in the contentment humilitie, and frugality, and that thou wert not either wretchedly couetous, arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly proud and of hauty Spirit, or profuſe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh in Gods bleſſings) and yet wilt thou liue of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? The Lord iudge betweene thee and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Is twenty, forty, fifty pounds, a ſufficiencie for Miniſters of good deſert, whom God accounteth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of double honour, and commandeth liberally to be rewarded, and can nothing be ſufficient for you (you wicked worldlings) but that you will needs rob God of his right, and his Miniſters of their due main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance? Is it his Miniſtery, or his perſon in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, vvhich you ſo meanely eſteeme of, that you can afford him no better reſpect? Surely his worke is <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.</note> a worthy worke, though a prophane <hi>Eſau</hi> account it of no valew, not worth a meaſe of pottage: and for that very worke ſake double honour is to be giuen to his perſon.</p>
            <p>What Pride then poſſeſſeth your hearts? is your vnderſtandings darkened? and hath the God of this world ſo blinded your eyes, that Gods Miniſters can merit at your hands no more, or the very beſt very little more (if you might haue your wils) for their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient maintenance, and yet you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udge your ſelues wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all that which you any way can come by, either in the Church or Common-wealth? in former times <note place="margin">Prouerb. 3. 9.</note> God was to be honoured with the chieſe of the peoples increaſe and riches, and may almoſt any thing now ſerue the turne? before times the Miniſtery was many wayes maintained, and had a tenth part beſides, and is now nothing but a tenth left ſomewhere, and inſteed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15732:21"/> of that tenth, ſcarce the hundreth part of the Parſonage remaining to the poore incumbent? Shall we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the law for ſo well prouiding? or ſhall wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the Goſpell? God forbid: let mens wicked co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe be condemned, and the perſons ſo infected be iuſtly cenſured. It vvas before deſtruction to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vp that, which was ſet apart for Gods ſeruice; <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 25.</note> and thinke you, that no plagues, no puniſhments, ſhall be poured out from God now vpon Sacriledgious Church-robbers? Shall our fathers giue liberally, and ſhall we take away? they gaue of their owne, ſo doe not you, neither will you ſuffer (which is a greater iniquitie) the Miniſters of Chriſt to inioy the free gift of other men. Well, goe on; buy, purchaſe, and poſſeſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly; yet know your ſinne, leaſt a perpetuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption come vpon your ſubſtance. Surely, vpon <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 8. 9.</note> the vnrighteous ſhalbe indignation and wrath, tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and anguiſh, and vpon the wicked will the Lord raine ſnares, fire and brimſtone, ſtormie tempeſt, and <note place="margin">Pſal. 11. 6.</note> this ſhall be their portion to drinke. And thus much for the firſt point, that a Miniſter is liberally to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: the ſecond followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>It is moſt meet that a Miniſters maintenance be as well certaine, as competent.</hi> So the Lord did ordaine vnder the law, that the Preiſts and Leuites might know <note place="margin">Miniſters maintenance ſhould be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</note> their due and right belonging vnto them: ſo now the the Lord ordaineth his Miniſters double honour, that they liue of the Goſpell, and that their hearers make them pertakers of all their goods. Hereby the people are certainly bound to maintaine them with an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable maintenance, how this may be to a iuſt ſumme ſhall appeare in the next point to be handled. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> And good reaſon is there that a Miniſters maintenance be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph. 4. 12. 13. Mat. 28. 19. 20.</hi>
               </note> certaine. The office of the Miniſterie is certaine vnto the end of the world; the execution thereof is impoſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15732:22"/> vpon him that is once lawfully called thereto, and to performe his office therein as certainely; the charge is <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 1. 2. 1 Cor. 9. 16.</note> great and waighty, and a woe remayneth to him, if hee doe not. It is therefore moſt meet, that with a certaine office, and the Miniſter bound as certainly to diſcharge that office, that there be alſo as certaine a maintenance to vphold the ſame, and to encourage ſuch in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their dutie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> If therefore you thinke the Miniſters worthy of maintenance, iudge it alſo very neceſſary that the ſame <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. 6. 6.</hi>
               </note> be certaine. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motiues. </seg>
               </label> The charge is certaine vpon them to looke carefully thereto with all diligence, and the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is as ſure, binding you to maintaine them. What letteth then, to make their maintenance certaine before men, which you in conſcience are bound to giue moſt certainely before God? verely not any thing: if you haue any vprightneſſe of conſcience to performe this duety to them, or care at all to vphold conſtantly the Miniſtery? If men be honeſtly minded they will as well make certaine that which they doe promiſe, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that which willingly they ſay they doe giue. But it may be people are delighted to hold their Teachers in ſuſpence, to make them more ſeruiceable to their wils, and more beholden to them, for that which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, they ſo voluntarily contribute; as if it were not deſerued; or that the labourer were not worthy of his hyre; or they not of duety bound to doe that which they doe, if they haue either faith in their words, truth in their profeſſion, or care of obedience towards God. Be like they would hold vp, or call vp againe among vs, the order of begging Fryars, and doe deſire to make Gods Miniſters bow to them for their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to whom they owe reuerence and double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for their Miniſtery. What is this voluntary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, but a tying of Miniſters to the pleaſure of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15732:22"/> the multitude, whoſe mindes remaine as conſtant, as <note place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue vpon meere voluntary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions.</note> the vveather-cocke? Who ſeeth not how this is to make the Miniſter to liue vpon almes, in ſome mens account, to pleaſe mens humours, to loſe their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ouer the people, to be baſely accounted of, euery day to expect their departure, ſo to liue vnquiet, in minde diſcontentedly, to conclude certainely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vvith themſelues for their continuing in any place? This tyeth vp their mouthes for telling the <note place="margin">Eſa. 58. 1.</note> people of their ſinnes, or the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> of their tranſgreſſions, leaſt ſuch voluntaries become male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, and turne their <hi>beneuolence,</hi> into <hi>maleuolence,</hi> This vvould hinder men from the ſtudy of diuinitie, and men of learning and gifts would not take vpon them the Miniſtery, if no better prouiſion were made for them, but to liue vpon mens meere good will, and at the pleaſure of the vntamed luſts of diſorderly and vnſtable multitudes. Hee that hath beene, or now is acquainted with beneuolences, can tell what cold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is in men this vvay. They are not like the Phariſie (though as much boaſting, perhaps, hauing leſſe cauſe) who would giue a tenth part, but as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complained in his time of the peoples ſtraite <note place="margin">De tempo. ſerm. 205.</note> heart and hand to the Miniſtery, ſaying, <hi>Tu vix mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſimam das:</hi> ſo may vvee complaine, that neither one nor other almoſt vvill giue ſcarce the thouſand part voluntarily. Some one, wee ſee, of an hundreth will giue ſomewhat largely, ſome other, a few, among thouſands will giue, but very ſparingly, ſo niggardly, as is a ſhame to tell, and the greateſt number nothing at all. The meaner ſort are found more willing, the rich able but few of them, very forward.</p>
            <p>Therefore in theſe luke-warme dayes, when peoples hearts are ſo ſtocken, or ſo variable and vnconſtant, ſo hardly well pleaſed, ſo ſoone diſpleaſed, ſo full of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15732:23"/> fantaſies, wherein yet the Miniſters muſt follow them, or elſe they ſhalbe diſcarded, it is reaſonable to any reaſonable man, to iudge it better for the Miniſter to liue vpon certainty, than vpon beneuolence, volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contribution, and vncertainties, for ſo, as a people ſhall deſire that a Miniſter ſhould abide vvith them conſtantly, ſo ſhould they be tyed to maintaine him as certainely: yea, this vvould tye a Paſtour to his flocke, if hee haue a minde contented, and the people to him, if they haue religion in them, knowing that neither part is at libertie, vvhen they liſt, vpon light occaſions, either to caſt other off; but to continue together, vvhile the one is taught and trained vp in the wayes of God, and his true worſhip painefully, and the other maintained in a certaine competent ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie. But now I come to the third and laſt point to <note place="margin">Tythes the fitteſt meanes to maintaine Miniſters.</note> be proued, how ſuch ſo competent maintenance may be made certaine, which I affirme to be by Tythes. The poſition is this.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That the beſt and moſt fit meanes for the certaine and ſufficient maintenance of Miniſters is by Tythes.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>
               </label> The holy men of God ſo iudged before the law, who paid <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 14. 18. and 28. 22.</hi>
               </note> tyth; tything out a tenth part vnto GOD, as <hi>Iacob</hi> vowed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>decima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> decimabo,</hi> they offred of the fruits of the ground, and of the increaſe <note place="margin">Gen. 4. Leu. 27. 30. Num. 18. 21.</note> of their cattell. This maintenance the Lord ratified vnder the law by plaine precepts, which hee gaue to the Leuites for the ſeruice of the Tabernacle. Tooke not Chriſt aright therein in the perſon of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 8.</note> approuing the paiment thereof in his time? the Apoſtle, ſaith, that the LORD hath <hi>ordained,</hi> or <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat 23. 23. 1 Cor.</hi> 9. 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> taken order for it, implying a ſtatute for the ſame; now let any ſhew what certaine maintenance did euer the Lord appoint for the Miniſtery, but tythe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? other things came in according to the ſeruice then in vſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15732:23"/> for the time preſent, and with the ſeruice of neceſſitie to ceaſe; but tythes before are not to be iudged cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, <note place="margin">Pet. Mar. com. Pl. p. 4. 236.</note> yet if then, not therefore now. When the Lord ſent peace vnto his Church, then were tythes brought in againe; the authority of Emperours, Kings, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, Eccleſiaſticall conſtitutions heretofore and yet daily approuing, confirming and commaunding the payment of the ſame; vvhich is ſo vvell knowne, as I neede not here ſet downe the ſame. Thus vve ſee it the wiſedome of God and his Church, before the law, vnder the law, and now vnder the Goſpell to iudge tythes to be the fitteſt meanes to maintaine the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, which alſo the very Heathen payed to the ſeruice <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutar. Lucul. &amp; Camil. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Hiſt. li. 12. cap.</hi> 14. 19. Reaſon.</note> of their Gods, to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> to <hi>Hercules,</hi> and other. The tenth part is a good portion, if it be truely payd, out of Gods bleſſing to euery man, for the Miniſter. The Hebrew word <hi>Decimauit,</hi> hath affinitie with another, that is, <hi>Diues fuit,</hi> for that a tenth is as a rich preſent, giuen vnto the Lord, which both God and his Church accepteth as a good meanes for the maintenance of Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Againe how can any <hi>Hearer</hi> make his Teacher par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all his goods any way better than by tything? moreouer no ſtypend in equall valew can be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for their maintenance, as tythes payd in kinde; they be ſufficient at all times, howſoeuer the price of things doe ariſe or fall, a Miniſter hath his part with the people in cheepe or deere yeeres: which maketh his liuing conſtantly anſwereable vnto the times, partaking with his pariſhioners, ſo as hee may haue a fellow-feeling of their proſperitie and aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and be thereby occaſioned vvith them to praiſe God, or to pray for them. By this euery one offereth vp ſomewhat vnto the vpholding of Gods ſeruice, howſoeuer deſerued on the Miniſters part, yet truely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15732:24"/> payd for the true worſhip of God, it is pleaſing to the Lord, and ſuch may looke for a bleſſing. We ſee by lamentable experience with vs, that where tythes are not payd, there is but beggarly maintenance for the Miniſter. Many hundreth of yeeres hath the cuſtome of paying tythes beene practiſed in the Church, and for any thing yet apparant, no better courſe hitherto can be found. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> For where this payment fayleth with vs, there the Miniſtery is neglected, Miniſters liue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poorely; no competency is left, but ſome beggar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtypend of ſome foure, ſixe, eight, or ten pounds <hi>numeratis pecunijt,</hi> not ſufficient to maintaine the life of a poore labourer: the Church-robbers ſtole away pounds and left pence, carryed away all the profits, and left a poore pittance, and the ſame alſo ſore charged vvith payments, vvhich may cauſe many to mourne, for the grieuous oppreſſion which lyeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them moſt heauily, and that without hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery, as far as they can ſee. <hi>O Couetous Crueltie! Sacrilegious impietie!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yeeld your ſelues therefore to the Lords vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">Motiues.</note> herein, the wiſedome of Gods Church, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Councels, the command of Princes, the practiſe of our right meaning fore-fathers, the deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our late Aunceſtours, though in other things, erring, by miſleading, yet herein to be greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. They were not after our mindes, but farre better diſpoſed, though they knew leſſe, but wee will needs be held religious, and yet liue of robbing Churches. <hi>O tempora, O mores!</hi> Our Aunceſtours did robbe themſelues to enrich the Church, (indeed in many things too much) but we robbe the Church, to enrich our ſelues, an vngodly change.</p>
            <p>But it may be you will ſay, for who will not ſay ſomewhat for himſelfe in theſe dayes, to defend or
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15732:24"/> excuſe his vvickedneſſe? that it is a great queſtion, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> whither the payment of tythes be lawfull; with whom? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> ſurely, either with idle headed Schiſmatickes, or Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgious ſinners; but who of ripe iudgement maketh it an <hi>vnlawfull</hi> thing to maintaine Miniſters by tythes? but if thou haſt a couetous ſcruple vpon this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not to pay tythes; be checked in thy conſcience likewiſe for with holding tythes, when ſollide reaſons are giuen againſt thy Sacriledgious ſinne, by very many learned Diuines. My meaning is not here to diſpute to and fro of this point with thee, for I referre thee to whole treatiſes of this matter (written by others:) But <hi>first</hi> know, that tythes is here in our Church the maintenance of the Miniſter; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that our Church (vvhereof thou art either a true, or counterfeite member) doth hold ſuch maintenance lawfull, and therefore till thou canſt either finde a better courſe, or conuince Her of an errour, let thy conſcience be (if thou haſt any) to yeeld to her determination, and beware of deciding the queſtion thy ſelfe, which is onely a couetous concluſion, from a prophane heart. But to come to that, which I moſt minde at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; thou canſt not deny, but, that the Miniſterie is Gods ordinance, that he hath appointed that his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters be maintained; thou haſt heard alſo, that this maintenance ſhould be ſufficient, and it cannot bee denied, but that tythes hath beene giuen for this end, and are payd in very many places ſtill to this purpoſe, onely in ſome places they be kept backe, and there the Miniſter hath not in any meaſure a competencie. <note place="margin">A heauy ſinne, to take tythes from the Church and not to leaue a competencie for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Miniſtery.</note> Now this is it which I would haue thee and all ſuch to know, that by your detayning of tythes from them (which is the onely ordinary meanes of maintenance vvith vs) not leauing any competencie to them, is your heauy ſinne, worſe then <hi>Achans</hi> theft, for which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15732:25"/> he receiued condigne puniſhment; yea, both hee and all his payd a heauy price for it: and know that Gods iuſtice ſleepes not, neither is his reuenging hand any whit ſhortened.</p>
            <p>Know you not, that <hi>Ananias</hi> and his wife did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <note place="margin">Marke and conſider theſe things you luke-warm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Goſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llers, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſerue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Mamoniſts, Hypocriticall profeſſours, and all other of the ranke of Atheiſts.</note> onely a part of the whole, and that which they themſelues had giuen to the Church, and yet death ſeazed vpon them both for the ſame; what then may you expect? vvhat death and deſtruction is due to you, who not onely giue nothing of your owne, but robbe the Church of that which was giuen by other men? the dead ſhall riſe vp in iudgement againſt you, you Canker-wormes. Conſider you not that the very name of <hi>Impropriation,</hi> telleth and conuicteth you of an vniuſt enioying of ſuch tythes, and that you are improper paſſeſſours of the ſame? Plead not a graunt from man, for what man can make good Sacril<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dge before GOD? plead not that thou art but onely a Farmar: an inferiour tranſgreſſer may periſh, though hee be not the principall actour in vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>You know that Antichriſt began this Sacriledge, and vvill you by verball profeſſion be great enemies to Poperie, and yet indeed, be to it great friends and followers in ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh a practiſe? <hi>deepe Hypocriſie!</hi> You vvill none of that religion, and yet liue of robbing: you proteſt againſt their vngodlineſſe (for you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the times) but you can very well digeſt their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, it is for your profit. <hi>Faithleſſe Hearts!</hi> Mamon is your God; whatſoeuer you pretend, he is <note place="margin">Moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> your Maiſter. Know you not, that by this Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robbing, many Congregations, and thoſe very great, hauing thouſands of poore ſoules in them are vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out competent maintenance to haue a preacher? Soules <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> precious to God, they did coſt the price of Chriſts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15732:25"/> bloud: and yet where there is no viſion the people pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: Oh then, ſhall your priuate profit becauſe of their deſtruction? <hi>Curſed gaine,</hi> to win euen a vvorld vvith damnation of ſoules. But ſuch places, ſay you, doe get themſelues preachers; yea, but ſo is enforced a double charge vpon the people, which your vnrighteouſnes cauſeth, and is this lightly to be regarded? Anſwere me now, I pray you, as you ſhall one day make an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before God and his Angels vnto Ieſus Chriſt: how can you comfort your ſelues in this damnable courſe? where is the word, your warrant, thus, for your owne profit, to vvithhold from your Miniſters, that vvhich ſhould maintaine them? What loue of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in you? vvhat reſpect of common good? vvhat compaſſion to mens ſoules? vvhat feeling of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthen which you cauſe your poore neighbours to beare, vvhen they pay you tythes, and yet muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides maintayne their Miniſter? Conſider you not that the hyre of the labourers is by you kept backe, and their cryes pierce the Heauens, and is entred into the eares of the Lord? Sinne you not againſt common equitie, muſling the Oxes mouth that treadeth out the Corne? Is not the labourer worthy to be rewarded? Doe you labour in Gods Vineyard? if not, why holde you from Chriſts Miniſters their neceſſary mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? Your manner is to lay all vpon the people, and your ſelues to allow nothing, or very little: this is the euilneſſe of your hearts, for the moſt part, that ſuch of you, as thus liue of Church-robbing, haue the leaſt conſcience of ſeruing God, and maintayning of the preaching of his Word. And no maruell that ſuch a curſe is vpon you, for the Miniſters maintenance, the peoples miſery, and great oppreſſion, religion, reaſon, and common equitie, the zeale of our forefathers, the good intendements of the dead doe call Heauen and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15732:26"/> Earth to witneſſe againſt this your couetouſneſſe, your crueltie to your neighbours bodies and ſoules, your owne hearts prophaneneſſe or hypocriſie, and this your ſinne and Sacriledge, and that God would iudge betweene you and them, and blow vpon your eſtates as he hath done vpon many already paſt and preſent; your fayre forewarnings.</p>
            <p>Conſider, how you open the aduerſaries mouths againſt our profeſſion; how they condemne our refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to be but a robbing of the Church, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring of that vvhich was ſet a part to the Lords ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Shame you not to bring ſhame vpon Gods Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell: ſhall other ſpoyle the Church, his Miniſters, and people, and feare you not to liue vpon the robberie!</p>
            <p>Conſider, how you, as I haue ſayd, profeſſe hatred to Idolatrie; and will you liue in Sacriledge? how dare you turne that to priuate profit, truely intended and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for publike good? how can you withhold from the Church, onely to maintaine your pride and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that which ſhould be for the Paſtours liuely hood, and the reward of his paynes in diligent teaching of his floc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e? and know you this? and ſhall not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration heereof reſtraine the rage of your couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but you vvill yet hold the owners from their right?</p>
            <p>Conſider, how the Lord hath curſed many ſuch rob-Churches; how their eſtates haue had vpon them a continuall conſumption: and ſhall not vvrath powred out, euen before your eyes, make you afrayd?</p>
            <p>Conſider with your ſelues, how theſe vvere giuen to the Miniſtery, how vvickedly they vvere taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, vvhat were the vniuſt grounds thereof, who were the parties, and the Lords anger againſt them. Alſo, what iuſt cauſe now to reſtore them againe, or at leaſt a ſufficient maintenance for them. Know you, that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15732:26"/> the Lord commaundeth you to maintaine your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and that they want maintenance, or that your neighbours muſt doe more than they may, and dare you liue in this rebellious diſobedience, not onely not to maintaine them, but to rob them, and to ſpoyle your brethren without ſence of their miſery? Oh heart that cannot repent! thou heapeſt vnto thy ſelfe wrath <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> againſt the day of vvrath, and the declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God.</p>
            <p>Conſider, vvith what face you can demaund the tenth part of the peoples labours, and ſee them want the meanes of ſaluation, for vvhich they pay theſe tythes? Doe you as you would be done vnto? verely no: for ſure and certaine it is, that, if the tythes were not in your owne hands, you could be very well content that they ſhould goe to the Church, and your Miniſters be maintayned by them. And can your hearts iudge ſo vprightly for your Miniſters in reſpect of other men? and is there no loue of equitie? no faith of truth? no power of conſcience? no regard of the Miniſtery? no neighbourly compaſſion? no ſtrength of grace, nor dread of God to make you equall and iuſt Iudges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your Miniſters and your ſelues, to yeeld them their right out of your owne hands? Ah partiall ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue and enemy to equitie and iuſt dealing!</p>
            <p>Conſider, with vvhat promiſe of a bleſſing, vvith what hope of mercie you can commend theſe goods to your poſteritie, ſo vniuſtly taken from the Church, ſo vnmercifully withheld by you, ſo needfull to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Church againe, for the peoples eaſe, euery way too deepely charged, and the Miniſters more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and liberall maintenance? Will you vainely thinke that your children ſhall thriue and doe well by your iniuſtice and wrongs, and by your wicked workes of inquitie? <hi>Oppreſſion ſhall bring thee to pouertie.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 16.</note>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:15732:27"/> 
               <hi>Hee that getteth riches, and not by right, ſhall leaue them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 17. 11.</note> 
               <hi>in the middeſt of his dayes, and at his end ſhall be a foole.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 11. and 14. 11.</note> 
               <hi>The riches of vanitie ſhall diminiſh, and the houſe of the wicked ſhall be deſtroyed;</hi> where is proſperous hope vnto poſterities in ill gotten goods?</p>
            <p>Therefore, that at length I may conclude this exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, vveigh theſe things well, ponder them in your hearts, conſider how you ſtand thus guiltie of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, how the Miniſters haue cauſe to mourne, how the people grieue, and may complaine to God, and how weakely, in deed and truth, you can oppoſe againſt that vvhich hath beene ſayd, that ſo you may yeeld li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall and ſufficient maintenance to your Miniſters, that God may repent of that he hath <hi>determined againſt you,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 25. Mal. 3. 9.</note> and you receiue a bleſſing to you and yours. Now be not like the foole, vvhich ſeeth the plague, yet goeth on, and is puniſhed. The wiſe man feareth, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <note place="margin">Pro. 14 16. Mal. 3. 8.</note> from euill, but a foole rageth and is careleſſe. The barbarous Heathen <hi>would not ſpoyle their Gods,</hi> and if any vvere ſo wicked among them (though God both hated them and their Idols, neuertheleſſe, becauſe hee would ſhew his deteſtation againſt ſuch as would wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a God, though but an Idoll, and yet rob him) ſuch vvould he plague and ſeuerely puniſh. The Heathen in their writings, beare witneſſe of this. The Grecians offering violence to the Temple of <hi>Pallas,</hi> neuer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered <note place="margin">Virg. <hi>li.</hi> Aene. 2. Lactan. <hi>de Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. error cap. 4.</hi>
               </note> after. An auncient Father reporteth, how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Heathen were grieuouſly puniſhed for offering violence to holy things. <hi>Euluitu</hi> the <hi>Cenſour,</hi> for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king tyles of Marble out of <hi>Iuno Lacinia</hi> her Temple, was ſhortly after diſtracted of his wits, and had two of <note place="margin">Cap. 8.</note> his ſonnes ſlaine. <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> was ſtrucken blind for alienating thoſe things which were conſecrate to <note place="margin">Iuſtin. <hi>hiſs. li. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hercules. Zerxes</hi> ſending foure hundreth Souldiers to ſpoyle the Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> they were deſtroyed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15732:27"/> and burnt vvith thunder and lightning. If God vvill reuenge the wrongs done to Heathen Gods, no Gods but Idols, in ſuch a terrible manner, (<hi>becauſe</hi> he will preſerue a reuerence of a conceiued God head in all mens mindes, though that conceit in a particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to an Idoll bee abhominable before him,) how much more will the Lord reuenge himſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe, which thus robbe his Sonne Chriſt, who is robbed in his ſeruants and Miniſters? let the wiſe bee iudge, and let beleeuers feare and tremble.</p>
            <p>Conſider in all this, what is ſaid vnto you, which poſſeſſe impropriations ſo iniurious to the Church. You Patrons alſo of Benefices, who nibble at, and pare away what you can get from thoſe vvhich you doe preſent, either by ſecret ſimoniacall compact, or by pretence of law, or elſe by force or fraud, ſome vvay or other to liue vpon Church-robbing ſacriledgiouſly. You Farmers of ſuch liuings conſider vvhat you doe, and you that gather vp the labours of the people, whereby the Miniſters of Chriſt are defrauded of their maintenance. You pilfering poore, and deceitfull payers of Tythes, which make no conſcience to ſteale ſomewhat away cloſely, with <hi>Achan,</hi> from the vſe of the Tabernacle; or vvith Hypocriticall <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> pretend that you pay tythes iuſtly, but yet keepe backe euer ſomewhat from the true owners thereof. Know your duetie, weigh the equitie of the cauſe, examine the former reaſons, conſider your ſins, and forſake your theft, that ye be not found written in that flying booke of vengeance, which commeth forth againſt theeues, to reuenge iniuſtice and wrong.</p>
            <p>If yet for all this ſome will not be moued to pay tythes, becauſe they now liue vnder the Goſpell. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of them, whither they meane honeſtly, that they can bee vvilling, in deed and in truth, to doe for the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15732:28"/> Church and Miniſters according to the time of the Goſpell? If you only diſclaime the law herein, becauſe of charges, and vvill not indeed yeeld to the times of the Goſpell, you but pretend Goſpell in Hypocriticall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, for that you thinke there is nothing to moue you to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e for your Miniſters maintenance; though the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rary hath beene already ſhewed. But goe to, I take you to ſpeake in a true meaning without cuaſions, we will be content to let the law goe, for this preſent, and will be willing to ſtand to the Goſpels re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <note place="margin">The Goſpell prouideth for Miniſters.</note> which is either the <hi>primary extraordinary practiſe,</hi> and that was a voluntary contribution, but ſo liberall, for the maintenance of the Miniſterie and brethren, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 37. &amp; 5.</note> as many ſold all they had, lands and poſſeſſions and brought the money, and layd the ſame downe at the <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 6.</note> Apoſtles feete: Or the <hi>Apostolicall precept,</hi> to make them pertakers <hi>of all</hi> your goods; or elſe the <hi>after act of the Church</hi> reſuming the payment of tythes.</p>
            <p>Now how like you theſe? chuſe for you ſelues, if the <hi>Laſt,</hi> that is it we would haue, and you diſlike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of aduantage; if the <hi>First,</hi> that is the beſt of all, but that we will not be ſo vnreaſonable towards you: for though you take all from vs, and the Church gaue all then, yet wee require but ſo much as is conuenient for vs to receiue, for vs to receiue, and you by duetie neceſſarily tyed to giue. We deſire not to be enriched, and you thereby impoueriſhed, that it now ſhould be ſaid, as heretofore, <hi>Religio peperit diuitias, ſed filia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorauit matrem,</hi> which I thinke wee need not to feare on our behalfe, as you, wiſely, neuer intend it on your parts. For it well appeareth, how much you loue to giue, as they did, freely, but not as they did liberally. I will ſay for you, that the firſt you diſlike, and better it were to giue a tenth part, than all. But will you reſt vvith the <hi>Second,</hi> and make the Miniſter pertaker of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15732:28"/> all your goods? Surely if you vvould performe this faithfully, wee might well reſt contented; for what is this, but to haue our wants liberally ſupplyed, and in you a franke heart to giue ſomewhat of what you get, of euery thing a part or ſhare, more or leſſe? elſe how can you make vs pertakers of <hi>all</hi> your goods? which, if you ſo vvould doe, is it a great matter, if we reape <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 11.</note> your carnall things, when we ſowe vnto you ſpirituall things? Thus you ſee (you pretending Goſpellers) that wee can reſt contented with the award of either the law or Goſpell, if you would conſcionably ſtand to either; but that indeed you are of neither, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they may ſerue your turnes, and be to you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. If I falſely accuſe you, conuince me by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and faithfully performing this duety you owe vnto the Miniſters of Chriſt, either according to law or Goſpell; if not, you muſt giue vs leaue to ſay, that you are worldly Atheiſts, of any religion for your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and commodities, profeſſing to know God, but by workes deny him, his Miniſtery, Miniſters, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to euery good worke reprobate.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
